<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter concerning the present state of religion amongst us</title>
            <author>Thorndike, Herbert, 1598-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1053</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5555</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12635903</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12635903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64862</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62458)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64862)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 337:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter concerning the present state of religion amongst us</title>
                  <author>Thorndike, Herbert, 1598-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Protesting the commonwealth's religious decrees.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Herbert Thorndike. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Subsequently published in various collections of his works.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64862:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER Concerning the preſent State OF RELIGION AMONGST US.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:64862:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64862:2"/>
            <head>A Letter concerning the preſent State of Religion amongst us.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y dear Brother in Chriſt, no leſſe then by birth; I have peruſed the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for ejecting of Scandalous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and finding it likely enough to ſend you a Paſtor, that ſhall have have no authority from the Church, have thought it neceſſary for me, to give you the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of that opinion which I declared unto you, that in that caſe, you ought not in conſcience to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſuch a for one your Paſtor, by going tohear him preach, and ſeeming to joyn in his Prayers, much leſſe to receive the Euchariſt at his hands, if ſuch a one ſhall be ſo audacious as to celebrate it.</p>
            <p>This that I may do, I muſt firſt propoſe the Caſe, as it is ſtated by thoſe Acts which pretend to ſettle Religion among us. For, firſt, the Act whereby the preſent Government is eſta<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſhed, declareth, that the <hi>Chriſtian Religion contained in the Scriptures ſhall be held forth, as the publick profeſsion of theſe Nations;</hi> And that, <hi>ſuch as profeſs Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt, though differing from this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, in doctrine, worſhip, or diſcipline,</hi> ſhal be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected in the exerciſe of their Religion, excepting Popery and Prelacy, and thoſe who under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of Chriſt, hold forth, and practiſe licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. In proſecution hereof an Ordinance is iſſued
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64862:3"/> forth, giving commiſsion to certain perſons, named in it, to examine and try all that have come into poſſeſſion of Churches ſince <hi>April.</hi> 13. 1653. all that have augmentations from Parliament, all that ſhall pretend to come into Churches that ſhall be void, whether fit for the Office and Benefice, by no other Rule, then the Certificate of three godly Neighbours, (one at leaſt a Miniſter) concerning their converſation in godlineſſe upon their own knowledge, and the judgement of five Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, that the grace of God is in their hearts, and that they are fit to preach. In further proſecution hereof, iſſues forth this Ordinance, whereby, no man is made ſcandalous for his judgement, but he that is liable to the Act againſt Blaſphemy of <hi>Aug.</hi> 9. 1653. And with him is ranked, he, who ſhall fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and publickly have read the Service ſince Chriſtmaſſe 1653. whereby it appeareth, that thoſe who have declared their perſeverance in the Religion which they have hitherto profeſſed, by reading the Service, are therefore counted ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; But thoſe that can obtain the certificate of ſuch men as theſe Triers count godly men, together with their own opinion, that ſo they are, and fit to Preach, are thereby qualified in Law, to be Paſtors of Pariſhes: And conſequently to ſucceed thoſe that adhere to the Chriſtianity which hitherto they have profeſſed, being caſt out by the Commiſſioners for ejecting of ſcandalous Miniſters.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place then, I ſay, that the effect of theſe Laws is, to nullifie, and make void one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Creed, which hithe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to to we profeſſe; To wit, the belief of one holy Catholick and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64862:3"/> Church. This word Church may ſignifie two things. Firſt, onely the whole number of Chriſtians; Secondly, a Communion and corporation of thoſe that profeſſe true Chriſtianity, founded by the will of God, and the miniſtery of our Lord Chriſt, and his Apoſtles. That Chriſtians, when they profeſſe to beleeve the Catholick Church, do not mean, that they beleeve that there is in the world a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men that profeſſe to be Chriſtians, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, becauſe all Chriſtians hope to be ſaved by their Faith: but they cannot hope to be ſaved, by beleeving that which they ſee; Now all men ſee, that there is ſuch a company of men in the world: therefore when they ſay, they beleeve the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, as part of that Faith, whereby they hope to be ſaved, they do not profeſſe to beleeve that there is ſuch a company of men, but that there is a Corporation of true Chriſtians, founded by our Lord Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which Hereticks and Schiſmaticks cannot have Communion with, and that they hope to be ſaved by this Faith, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing members of it. And this is that, which the ſtile of the holy Catholick and Apoſtlick Church ſignifies, as diſtinguiſhing the Body of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, (to wit, ſo far as profeſſion goes) from the Conventicles of Hereticks and Schiſmaticks. For this title of Catholick would ſignifie nothing, if Hereticks and Schiſmaticks were not barred the Communion of the Church. And let no man imagine, that the Schiſme which the Reformation hath made between us and the Church of Rome, hath diſſolved the obligation of being members of the Church: if that change which is called Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64862:4"/> preſerve not ſuch a Church, as ought to be acknowledged for a true member of the whole, or Catholick Church, it is no Reformation, but the deſtruction of Chriſtianity. Now when theſe Laws inable Souldiers, and Juſtices of the Peace, as well as thoſe that call themſelves Miniſters, to make publick Preachers; as well ſuch as have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no Ordination from the Church, as thoſe that have; It is manifeſt, that all difference between Clergy and People, is by them diſſolved, and made void; And by conſequence, the Corporation of the Church, which grounds and creates all the difference, which hitherto by all Chriſtians hath been received, between theſe two qualities. True it is, that for the preſent, as well thoſe who have law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful authority to officiate the publick Service of God by Ordination from the Church, are admitted or maintained in their Benefices by theſe Laws, as thoſe that have none; Though it be wel enough known, that thoſe who have ſuch authority do pretend to act by vertue of it, and not by this Law, further then, as by ſubmitting to it, they remove that force, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders their right, otherwiſe gotten, to take effect. But it is as true, that ſuppoſing this Law to continue an age, none ſuch can remain. And when none ſuch remains, then there ſhall be no Church in <hi>England,</hi> but by equivocation of words, if the premiſes be be true. And therefore, thoſe that acknowledge ſuch as have <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o other authority but from this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for their Paſtors, cannot conſequently profeſſe to beleeve one Catholick Church, nor hope for ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by being members of it. For ſuppoſing for the preſent, though not granting, that the power which makes theſe Laws is from God, yet can it not be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64862:4"/> pretended to be from our Lord Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. And therefore this authority derived from it, cannot be derived from any act of theirs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting the Church, and inabling it to give this authority, by acknowledging whereof, Chriſtians preſume that they are members of the Church.</p>
            <p>Now that you may ſee why the belief of Chriſts Church is an Article of our Creed; I ſay further, that you cannot acknowledg ſuch men for your Paſtors, becauſe you are not ſecured by theſe Laws, that they are not Hereticks. For, ſeeing the Act of Eſtabliſhment pretends onely to <hi>hold forth the Chriſtian Religion contained in the Scriptures,</hi> and that all the Hereſies that are this day in the world, do maintain themſelves to profeſſe the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion contained in the Scriptures, it is manifeſt, that theſe Laws provide not, that they ſhall not be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, which are ſent you for Paſtors. Here I muſt not complain, that, whereas all that profeſſe Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt, though differing from the profeſſion held forth, are protected in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Religion, Pop<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry and Praelacy are excepted; though it cannot be denied, that both profeſs Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt. Nor, that, thoſe who hold the profeſſion eſtabliſhed by the Laws under which we were born, are reſuſed that protection, which is tendred Socinians, enemies of the Trinity and ſatisfaction of Chriſt, who manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſs Chriſtian Religion contained in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt. For, my bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is not to ſay, what they that made theſe Lawes, ſhould have done by them; but, what you are to do now they are made. But, if it be anſwered, that,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64862:5"/> thoſe that make theſe Lawes, repoſe truſt in them to whom they grant theſe Commiſſions, that they will not take any to be godly men that are Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; To this I ſay, that will not ſerve your turn for ſeveral reaſons. For, thoſe that profeſſe all that the Law requires them to profeſſe, that is, <hi>Faith in God through Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtian Religion Contained in the Scriptures,</hi> cannot be judged ungodly for whatſoever they profeſſe beſides, by any Power derived from this Law, but by an arbitrary power to be exerciſed at the will of the Commiſſioners. And, how are you aſſured that no Heretick ſhall obtain a certificate of three Neighbours, and ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer their demands, that they ſhall have cauſe to think him in Gods grace? However; you are not warranted to truſt your ſalvation, and the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe that depend on you, either upon the judgement of theſe Commiſſioners, or of them that make the laws. If it be demanded, why the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Power, and the Commiſſioners thereof are not as well to be truſted with the ſalvation of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as thoſe that may pretend authority from the Church? the anſwer is ready: That, when you acknowledge a Paſtor ſent by the Church, you nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truſt his perſon, nor the perſon of him that ſends him, but the Laws which the Church hath received from our Lord and his Apoſtles: in as much as, by profeſſing Chriſtianity ſo limited, and according to them to exerciſe the function which he receiveth, he becomes qualified for the charge in which you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him: which Laws he that deſtroyes, by diſſolving the Corporation of the Church, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes the truſt you are to have in thoſe whom
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64862:5"/> you acknowledge your Paſtors, that they are not Hereticks.</p>
            <p>And here I muſt not fail to give you notice, that thoſe Presbyterians and Independents, who, having departed from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of erecting Presbyteries and Congregations, do now make themſelves Commiſſioners to execute theſe Laws, which deſtroy both Presbyteries and Congregations; have thereby deſtroyed the ground of all truſt which the Church might have had in them, for conduct in Chriſtianity. For what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion can it be preſumed that they will hold, when they hold not that, for which they have deſtroyed the Unity of the Church? which is the reaſon, why Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, though they may be re-admitted to the Communion of the Church upon repentance, yet, by the Rules of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church cannot be re-admitted to be of the Clergie. Theſe Apoſtacies having made them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of that truſt, which the Church muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily repoſe in the Clergy.</p>
            <p>That you may ſee this is not for nothing, I ſay further, that there is among us a damnable Hereſy of Antinomians, or Libertines, formerly, when Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans were not divided from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> known by the name of Grindletonians and Etoniſts. Theſe, do beleeve ſo to be ſaved by the free grace of God, by which Chriſt died for the Elect, that true faith is nothing but the revelation hereof, and by conſequence, that all their ſins, paſt, preſent, and to come, being remitted by this grace; to repent of ſin, or to contend againſt it, is the renouncing of Gods free grace, and ſaving faith.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:64862:6"/>
            <p>Another opinion there is, which I cannot ſay the Presbyterians hold, or require to be held; but in regard their confeſſion of Faith, and Catechiſme diſclaimes it not, and therefore allows them that hold it to be of their Faction, may well be ſaid to maintain it; That, for a man to beleeve that he is praedeſtinate to life, and that Chriſt died for him, is that faith, which alone juſtifieth a Chriſtian. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe opinions is the better, or the worſe, or, what is the difference between them, let the parties diſpute. This I ſay, that, allowing the merits and ſatisfaction of Chriſt to the Elect for remiſſion of ſins, and a title to everlaſting life, in no conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but of their perſons, it is more reaſonable to ſay, that they can never become guilty of ſin, then, that the remiſſion of their ſins, and their right to life, ſhould depend upon the knowledge of their prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination revealed by Faith: ſeeing nothing is true becauſe it is beleeved, but beleeved becauſe it is true. And therefore, I ſay, that both of theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions are deſtructive to the foundation of faith which the Church of <hi>England</hi> teacheth, when, in the Office of Baptiſme, and the beginning of the Catechiſme, it requireth all that are baptized, not onely to profeſs the Faith of Chriſt, <hi>but to renounce the fleſh, the world, and the devil, and to fight with them till death, for the keeping of Gods Commandments, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring them hereupon, that they are regenerate and adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Gods children by his Grace in Chriſt.</hi> For he that is ſaved by undertaking and perſevering in this, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be ſaved by beleeving, that he is abſolutely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate to life without it. For, I muſt ſay, that it is one thing to be abſolutely predeſtinate to life;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64862:6"/> another thing to be predeſtinate to life, by being abſolutely predeſtinate to perſevere till death. For he that is predeſtinate to life, by being abſolutely predeſtinate to perſevere in the Covenant of Grace till death, is predeſtinate to life in conſideration of the Covenant of Grace, in which he is predeſtinate to perſevere. And whether a man can be abſolutely predeſtinate to perſevere in it, of his own free-will, and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary choice, or not, is that which remaines in diſpute among Divines, which I ſuppoſe not here, to be either true or falſe. But to ſay, that a man is abſolutely predeſtinate to life, and to ſay, that he is predeſtinate to life, in conſideration of his undertaking and perſevering in the Covenant of Grace, which muſt be the act of his own free-will and choice, is to ſay expreſs contradictions, and to deſtroy the Covenant of Grace, (into which, by the Baptiſme of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> every man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth) and all hope of Salvation, which is meerly imaginary, if not grounded upon it. Seeing then, that the trial upon which theſe Commiſſioners pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, is, the marks of predeſtination, whether true or falſe, not diſtinguiſhing whether they ſuppoſe the Covenant of Grace, the undertaking of it, and perſevering in it, or not; I ſay, that you are no way ſecured by theſe Laws, that the Triers themſelves, much leſſe thoſe whom they ſhall ſend you, are not complices of this damnable Hereſy.</p>
            <p>I muſt not forget to adviſe you, that <hi>Dell,</hi> one ſo far of this Hereſy, that he hath written a Book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Baptiſme it ſelf, is now, and is acknowledged by theſe Commiſſioners, maſter of a Colledge in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64862:7"/> Univerſity, (whereof ſeveral fellows have been no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Preachers of this Hereſy) who cannot be acknowledged a member of the Church by any good Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>The like I alledge in regard of the Sect of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts. In which point I muſt ſuppoſe two things. Firſt, that the Chriſtian Faith ſuppoſeth Original ſin. Secondly, that without Baptiſme there is no cure for it; which depends upon the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, that there is no abſolute predeſtination, without conſideration of the Covenant of Grace, which Baptiſme executeth, to cure it. For, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever our Lord meant, when he ſaid, <hi>unleſſe ye be born again of water</hi>—it is manifeſt, that, though no man can become a true Chriſtian, without the operation of the Holy Ghoſt, yet the Grace of the Holy Ghoſt dwelling in a man, is not granted, but, in conſideration of his entring into the ſaid cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and that this onely is the cure of Original ſin. There is then no neceſsity of ſhewing an expreſſe precept in Scripturre, that all Infants be baptized: or that the Church from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time did Baptize all while they were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants. If the Chriſtian Faith ſuppoſe Original ſin, if no cure for that, but by the covenant of Grace, if no execution of that Covenant, but the Baptiſme of the Church, (unleſſe, where the outward act is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by inevitable neceſſity, after the inward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thereof was ſufficiently reſolved and declared) then is this neceſſity a conſtraining precept, and hath been ſo reputed by the Church, even ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; which alwayes hath taken order, not that all ſhould be baptized Infants, but that no Infant
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64862:7"/> ſhould die without being baptized. For, the diligent watch over all occaſions, that might carry Infants out of the world unbaptized, obſerved by the Church from the beginning, though neglected ſince, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrateth, no legal aſſurance of the ſalvation of ſuch as ſhould die unbaptized, whatſoever might be preſumed of Gods goodneſſe over and above what he declareth. But, as for thoſe that ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come obliged and engaged to the covenant of grace, by being conſecrated to God through the act of the Church, thereby obliging it ſelf to ſhew them the truth of Chriſtianity, which obligeth all to whom it is ſhown; the neceſſity aforeſaid, together with the practice of the Church, is a legal preſumption, of the cure of Original ſin, and the opening of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, which it onely ſhutteth. If therefore our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts do not believe original ſin, they are Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagian Hereticks. If, beleeving it, they beleeve not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, that it is cured by Predeſtination without the Covenant of Grace, they fall into the damnable Hereſy premiſed: And ſeem to make, not onely that Baptiſme whereby they make void the Baptiſme received in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of the Chriſtianity which they received and profeſſed at their Baptiſme; but, that alſo, which they give thoſe whom they will not have baptized while they are infants, utterly void, and ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al towards God, as not pretending to bring them into Covenant of Gods Grace by Chriſt, that is, into the profeſſion of the true Faith, and of figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt ſin till death, under the ſame: which, they that beleeve Salvation by Gods Predeſtination revealed by faith, without undertaking and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64862:8"/> in the Covenant of Grace, can by no means pretend to do. Seeing then, that the neceſſity of Baptiſme cannot be denied, but upon ſuch a ground, as voideth the Covenant of Grace, and ſeeing the Triers are either Anabaptiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or complices in the ſame Commiſſion with Anabaptiſts (whereof there are in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Triers, five or ſix that I hear of by name, and how many more God knows, and in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for ejecting of ſcandalous Miniſters, in one County of Hertford, nine of fifteen, as I am cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly informed) it is evident, that, by theſe Laws, you are no wayes ſecured of having Anabaptiſts for your Paſtors, who are expreſsly Schiſmaticks (forſaking the Church for that which the Church alwayes did), and, by conſequence of the premiſed reaſons, Hereticks.</p>
            <p>As the Baptiſme of thoſe men whom they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſend you for Paſtors, is, by this reaſon, void in point of right, ſo the Euchariſt which they may pretend to celebrate, will be void of the effect of a Sacrament toward you, but not void of the crime of Sacriledge towards God. The reaſons are two. The firſt, becauſe thoſe who have not received the Order of Prieſthood ſhall pretend to celebrate it. For, the Scripture, interpreted by the un-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted practiſe of the Church, allows no man, under the Order of a Prieſt, to celebrate the Euchariſt. Not, as if thoſe who call themſelves Miniſters did commit this Sacriledge, in conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Euchariſt: Though the name of Miniſters ſignifies no more then deacons, and, that it is truely
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64862:8"/> Sacrilege for deacons to celebrate the Euchariſt: But, becauſe thoſe whom the Church lawfully gives not the power of celebrating this Sacrament to, (though, by miſ-underſtanding, thoſe whom it gives it to, may be called Miniſters, and ought to be called Prieſts) their Euchariſt is no Sacrament, but Sacrilege. The ſecond, becauſe they know not, nor acknowledge, the Conſecration, that is requiſite to the celebration and beeing of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, by the ſame Scriptures, underſtood ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the un-interrupted cuſtome and practice of the Church. For, the whole Church of God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the elements conſecrated to be the Body and Bloud of Chriſt myſtically, or in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, alloweth this change to be made by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, before which they were onely Bread and Wine. Not, as if after the Conſecration they were not ſo, but becauſe they are then become that which they were not afore, to wit, the Sacrament of Chriſts Body and Bloud, or the Body and Bloud of Chriſt ſpiritually, and myſtically, that is, in the Sacrament. This Conſecration being exactly maintained by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they that preſume to celebrate the Euchariſt, without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the fame, and pretending to deſtroy the Law by which it is exerciſed, muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, not to acknowledge the neceſſity thereof, to the being of this Sacrament. And therefore, they, and their complices in the Communion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to be guilty of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, as not diſtinguiſhing a ſigne of mans inſtitution from a Sacrament of Gods appointment and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64862:9"/>
            <p>As for the Office of Preaching and Praying, which they pretend to, in behalf of the Church, I will mark you out two monſtrous Impoſtures, in all the Sects of this time. The firſt is this ground of the bleſſed Reformation of Religion in <hi>England;</hi> That the Church is not to aſſemble for the Service of God, but when there is preaching. This ſeems to ſtand upon a very groſſe miſtake, of thoſe paſſages of the Apoſtles writings, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, the neceſſary means of ſalvation to conſiſt, in hearing the Goſpel preached; As if they were meant of Sermons in the Pulpit, which are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made to thoſe that are already Chriſtians, not of publiſhing the Goſpel to thoſe that knew it not afore, convincing them that it is true, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them wherein it conſiſts. Or, as if thoſe that are already Chriſtians wanted any thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation, ſuppoſing them to perſevere in the Chriſtianity which they have profeſſed. Not as if their Chriſtianity did not oblige them to hear Sermons, when the authority of the Church aſſures them to be without offence; But, becauſe, the Offices of publick Praiers, and the Praiſes of God, eſpecially in celebrating the bleſſed Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, are the end of all that inſtruction in Chriſtianity, which Chriſtians receive from the Church; and therefore, all Preaching ſubordinate to the ſame, as the means to the End: And becauſe, they may be daily ſo frequented, without offence, and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the reverence of Chriſtianity, as the experience of our time ſhows, that Preaching cannot be. The ſecond is, that, the firſt day of the week, called Sunday, is the Sabbath, by force of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64862:9"/> the fourth Commandement. An Impoſture ſo groſs, that it may well ſerve for an inſtance, what Faction can do, with men that are ſober otherwiſe. That God, by commanding the Jews to keep the ſeventh day of the week, to wit, that day on which he ended the Creation of the world, and, for that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reaſon commanding it, ſhould be thought to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Chriſtians to keep the firſt day of the week, on which he began the Creation, and our Lord Chriſt aroſe from the dead; That is, that the ſame words of the ſame Commandment in writing, ſhould oblige Jews to reſt on the Saturday, which oblige Chriſtians to reſt on the Sunday, is a thing, which when this fit of frenſy ſhall be paſt us, will ſcarſe be beleeved, that ever any man would beleeve. True it is, this firſt day hath been obſerved, in, and ever ſince the Apoſtles time, but not by vertue of that Law, which their office was to declare was expired, and out of date; but, by the Act of their own authority, whereby they gave Laws to Chriſts Church. Let us now onely compare the daily morning and evening Sacrifice of Prayer and the Praiſes of God, eſtabliſhed by the Order of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> together with the more ſolemn ſervice of Lords dayes and Feſtivals, with a bare Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon upon Sundaies, uſhered in and out with a Prayer of every mans own conceit, (ſetting aſide the Hereſy and falſe doctrine, the Faction &amp; Schiſm, the blaſphemy and ſlander, the ridiculous follies which this Sermon and Prayer may, and which we have known them contain) I ſay, comparing theſe together, the bleſſed reformation pretended, is and ought to be accounted, the abomination of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, in compariſon of that Order which it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64862:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> And therefore upon this account alone, thoſe, who, not being inveſted with that ordinary Power by which the Church is inabled to correct abuſes in the Church, ſhall uſurp the Power of the Church to introduce this diſorder, are thereby Schiſmaticks themſelves, and thoſe that acknowledge them for their Paſtors, complices of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</p>
            <p>It will be ſaid, that theſe Laws will be amended, as it was many times ſaid awhile ſince, that the Parliament would ſettle a Miniſtery. To this I ſay, that thoſe that are ſent you by virtue of theſe Laws, have every way as good authority, as any, the Power that made theſe Laws, joyned with a Parliament can give to them, that are not otherwiſe qualified by the authority of the Church. That is, that this Power of a Parliament together, though, adviſing with divines, how the qualities of thoſe whom they make Miniſters are to be limited, can do no more, then this Power, with adviſe of thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines it uſeth, hath done: Both being Secular, and able to make men their Miniſters, to maintain the Intereſt of that Government which their Power conſtituteth, but not Miniſters of the Church, to maintain the intereſt of that Faith, and ſervice of God, which it is truſted with. If it be ſaid, that, at the Reformation, thoſe from whom the Miniſtry is propagated, had not received by their Ordination, Power to ordain others; I anſwer, that, it is agreed among all that profeſſe the Reformation, that the abuſes crept into the Church were ſo great, that particular Churches, that is, part of the whole,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64862:10"/> might, and ought to reform themſelves, without conſent or concurrence of the whole: It is alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed among them that maintain it, that, there is in the Church a ſucceſſion of perſons, indued with authority in behalf of it, as well as of doctrine, and of the ſervice of God; Though the ſucceſſion of perſons be of leſs conſideration, as ſubordinate to the ſucceſſion of doctrine, as the means to the end. In this caſe then I ſay, that, ſuch inabilities, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons veſted with Eccleſiaſtical Power by the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as became unavoidable by the refuſal of the reſt of the Church to concur in it, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make Churches ſo conſtituted, no Churches, nor void the effect of thoſe Offices which perſons ſo qualified ſhall miniſter unto Gods people. But, ſuch inabilities, as became unavoidable, onely for want of due information in thoſe that undertook to reform themſelves, as it would be malice in man to juſtifie, ſo, it may reaſonably be preſumed, that the mercy of God excuſes. But ſuppoſing, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the premiſes, and the ſenſe of all that adhere to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians Ordinations tend no more to maintain the primitive faith and ſervice of God, once delivered to the Church, and eſtabliſhed in it by the Apoſtles, then they do to maintain that which is hitherto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> I ſay ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this, to imagine, that an Aſſembly of Divines, by being lawfully ordained to the office of Prieſts or Deacons, according to the Laws of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> can by commiſſion from the ſecular Power, make ordinations, which the Laws under which they were ordained forbid, is to imagin,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64862:11"/> that God can inable man to ſin, or, that a Soveraign Power can authorize the ſubject to rebell againſt it ſelf. And therefore, though the qualities of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be ſent you for Paſtors may be otherwiſe limited by Acts which Parliaments may make, yet theſe qualities, (not being derived from the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Apoſtles ſounding the Church, by any act of the Church, but from ſecular Power, and Commiſſion iſſued from it) make them no more Miniſters of the Church, that are made by Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of Divines and Presbyteries, then thoſe that are made by commiſſion of Triers, and ejecting ſcandalous Miniſters: That is, both of them, being by their creation Schiſmaticks, and their profeſſion not clearing them of miſpriſion of Hereſy, they can no more be acknowledged by thoſe that pretend to adhere to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then Belial by Chriſt, or darkneſſe by light.</p>
            <p>Hereby then you may conclude how to receive thoſe, whom the Presbyt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rians may ſend you for Paſtors, by any change in the ſecular Power. For I charge not them, that they do not beleeve the Church: which they would be themſelves. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that they ſecure you from all Sects but themſelves. But in as much as they maintain Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination to life, onely in conſideration of what Chriſt hath already done or ſuffered for the Elect; in ſo much, I ſay, that they do not, nor can Baptize into the Croſs of Chriſt; that is to ſay, into the hope of Salvation, in conſideration of fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fleſh, the world, and the Devil, for the keeping of Gods commandements, under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Chriſtian Faith. For, that which is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64862:11"/> abſolutely due, as ſalvation is due to the elect by the gift of Gods Praedeſtination, cannot be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened with any condition of Chriſtianity after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. And therefore that Baptiſme is no effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Baptiſme before God, (if Baptiſme received in the Church of <hi>England</hi> be ſuch) that is to ſay, it is no Baptiſme, but by Equivocation of words, in as much as, the obligation of a mans Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity is not declared, or underſtood, to take hold of him, by vertue of it. For ſeeing the hope of ſalvation which Chriſtians have by their Baptiſme is grounded upon the condition of their Chriſtianity, that Baptiſme which promiſeth ſalvation without providing for this condition, is no Baptiſme, but by equivocation of words. I ſay further, that the change, which they call Reformation, viſibly tends, to introduce that monſtrous impoſture of two Sermons every Sabbath, in ſtead of the daily and ordinary ſervice of God, (together with the more ſolemn ſervice of God upon Feſtivals and Lords daies, and other extraordinary occaſions) which the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with the whole Church of God from the beginning hath maintained, ſo far, as there was means to maintain it. I will not here inſiſt upon the order of Biſhops, and their chief power in their Dioceſes, as of Divine Right, that is, inſtituted and introduced by the Apoſtles. Let The Presbyterians think themſelves priviledged to erect altar againſt Altar, upon ſo deſperate a Plea, as now they inſiſt upon, that the Presbyteries are rather of divine right, then the chief Power of Biſhops, in their Dioceſes; I inſiſt now onely, that this Power of the Biſhops, was not againſt Gods Law: which every man muſt grant me, that acknowledges a Church in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64862:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> from the Reformation till now. In this caſe, they, who, to introduce this Chriſtianity, and this publick exerciſe of it, tranſgreſſing that authority to which they were called by the viſible act of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> take upon them, to ſhare that Power from which they had their authority, among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and, to execute it by conſent among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in their ſeveral precincts, cannot be ſaid to conſtitute a Church, by vertue of any act of the Apoſtles, or any authority derived from ſuch act, but by vertue of their own act, as all Apoſtates and uſurpers do; That is to ſay, that, they do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute ſuch a Church, by being a member whereof a man may reaſonably aſſure himſelf of ſalvation, upon any principle of Chriſtianity, but ſuch a Church, as is indeed no Church, unleſſe it be by equivocation of termes, but a conventicle of Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks with miſpriſion of the Hereſy aforeſaid. And therefore their Prieſthood is no Prieſthood, their Euchariſt is no Euchariſt, (unleſſe it by equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation of words) but Sacrilege againſt Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Beſides, that, what is requiſite to the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration thereof, or, wherein it conſiſts, they ſeem to be as ſecure of, and as little to regard; as the moſt ignorant of thoſe ſects into which the once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon name of Puritans ſtands divided at this time. Neither is it in any ſecular Power, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo unqueſtionable, to cure theſe nullities and incapacities, in the pretenſe, upon which they take upon them to be a Church; Though for the preſent they are not ſo much as authorized to the world, by any priviledge or penalty enacted by any ſecular Power, but onely protected by it.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64862:12"/> That all the world may ſee, that there is nothing but their own uſurpation, and the conſent of thoſe whom they have debauched to their Schiſme, whereby they ſubſiſt as a Church: And, that they will, by vertue of their Original, be as malignant to any ſecular Power, that ſhall not maintain and authorize them, as ever they were to that which they have deſtroyed, to introduce this ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a Church.</p>
            <p>If it be objected, that your Eſtates will be lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Penalties, that may be enacted againſt thoſe that withdraw from the exerciſe of the Religion publickly held forth; To this I have no anſwer, but, that wee are to obey God rather then man, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the next world before this, and to bear Chriſts Croſſe, if we expect his kingdom. Onely thus much I muſt obſerve, that theſe Laws proceed from a profeſſion, that it is not lawful to force mens Conſciences, in matter of religion, by penalties. And therefore, though the Praelatical party are not protected in the exerciſe of their Religion, yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not they be puniſhed for it, but by denying that which is declared upon the publick Faith. Beſides, acknowledging <hi>the Chriſtian Religion contained in the Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>profeſsing faith in God, by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> they are as much qualified for protection, as thoſe that are protected by the act of eſtabliſhment. And, not to allow the exerciſe of that Religion, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion whereof is not diſallowed, ſeems to bee, to forbid men to be Chriſtians who are not forbidden to be ſuch Chriſtians, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to popular tumult, contrary to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64862:13"/> peace, whom no Law puniſhes. If the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts continue nevertheleſſe liable to former Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, perhaps it is becauſe they are reputed Idolaters. But becauſe theſe laws, and the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from whence they proceed, may change, I muſt confeſſe, you cannot follow my advice, but that your eſtate may become queſtionable: Neither would I give it, could I aſſure you of the kingdom of heaven otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>If you demand what means I can ſhew you to exerciſe your Religion, withdrawing from the means which theſe Acts provide: I anſwer, that there are hitherto, every where, of the Clergie, that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Church, who will finde it their duty, to ſee your infants Chriſtned, your children Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed, the Euchariſt communicated to all thar ſhall withdraw from Churches forcibly poſſeſſed by them whom you own not for Paſtors. And if they cannot continually miniſter to you, ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed, the ordinary Offices of Gods ſervice; you have the Service of God according to the Order of the Church, you have the Scriptures to read for part of it, you have ſtore of Sermons manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allowed by the Church to read, you have Prayers preſcribed for all your own neceſſiti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and the neceſsities of the Church; To ſerve God with theſe in private, with ſuch as depend upon you, and are of the ſame judgement with you (leaving out what belongs to the Prieſts office to ſay) I do, to the beſt of my judgement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve an acceptable ſacrifice to God, which you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64862:13"/> cannot offer at the Church in ſuch caſe. And though I cenſure not my brethren of the Clergy, that think fit to comply with the power which we are under in holding or coming by their Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (I ſuppoſe in reſpect of their ſlocks, rather then to their fruits) yet, if they beleeve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their flocks, to be members of Gods Church, by being members of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> they muſt needs beleeve, thoſe flocks that acknowledge ſuch Paſtors, to be members of no Church, and therefore acknowledge you, and own your departure, and declare themſelves to their own flocks, and inſtruct them to do the like, when the like caſe falls out: And ſo the reſuſing to hear the voice of ſtrangers, will unite us to make a flock, under thoſe whom we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our lawful Paſtors.</p>
            <p>I have found my ſelf preſſed, to Print Copies hereof, for mine own uſe, thereby to declare thus much of my judgement to you, and to the reſt of my friends, becauſe the conſequence of owning ſuch men for your Paſtors, will be, to make us mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of ſeveral Churches. Which muſt diſable me, to do any office of a Clergy man towards you; unleſſe it be the proſecuting of this, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you further reaſons, to juſtify what I ſay here, and to reduce you to it: Though it ſhall alwayes be my ſtudy, faithfully to ſerve my kinred and friends, in all Offices of civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. And I hope they will conſider, what
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64862:14"/> appearance there is that any thing ſhould move me, to make my ſelf liable to ſo much harm, as the publick declaring of this opinion will make me liable to, but the diſcharge of my conſcience to God and them, as the caſe ſhall require me to diſcharge it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64862:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
